[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here an extremely
common type of reaction in organic
chemistry involves some nucleophile
attacking a carbonal carbon often in the
form of an alahh or Ketone what are
these nucleophiles and what kinds of
compounds can be produced let's check
out a few examples when a nucleophile
attacks a carbon carbon it will do so at
a specific angle called the Bergie dunit
angle which is around 75° from the
horizontal this is so that it can access
the lowest unoccupied molecular orbital
and bond to the carbon thus Shifting the
carbonal carbon from SP2 to sp3
hybridized this pushes the pi Bond up
onto the oxygen to generate the
oxyanion generally this is then
protonated to give the alcohol what
kinds of nucleophiles are capable of
this transformation many of them are
negatively charged such as hydroxide
hydde carbanion alkoxide or cyanide but
sometimes even neutral nucleophiles can
attack the carbonal these include water
alcohol ammonia or other
amines sometimes depending on the
identity of the nucleophile we don't
stop at the alcohol instead the alcohol
can be further proteinated and a second
Bond can form from the nucleophile to
what was originally the carbonal carbon
resulting in a pi bond this will
frequently happen with amines which will
attack the carbonal but then proton
transfer will occur such that the same
nitrogen can attack again kicking water
off and producing what is called an
imine in terms of reactivity alahh are
generally more reactive than ketones in
the context of nucleophilic addition
both for steric and and electronic
reasons sterically there is one less
alkal group projecting from the carbonal
so a nucleophile can more easily
approach but also an alahh carbonal is
slightly more polarized than a ketone
because alkal groups are slightly
electron donating through induction so
the carbonal carbon is not quite as
partially positive in a ketone as it is
for an alahh to extend this to aromatic
systems something like benzal deide will
be less reactive than an aliphatic alahh
because of the resonance from the
Benzene ring which makes the carbonal
carbon less
electrophilic there is much more we can
do with alahh and ketones in the way of
nucleophilic substitution but for now
that serves as a reasonable introduction
Professor Dave for che see you next time
[Music]
go